University Art Museum; Records ua601.005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Art Museum Records
1997 June 16 - 2013 June 1
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua601.005
3.33 cubic ft.
69 captures
Records of the Art Museum that was built on UAlbany's Uptown Campus with the support of Governor Nelson Rockefeller.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this collection is restricted because it is unprocessed. Portions of the collection may contain recent administrative records and/or personally identifiable information. Please contact an archivist for more information.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Kenneth D. Mosher, Jr., Class of 1946. 1998
Administrative History
The University Art Museum was officially opened and dedicated on October 5, 1967 as the University Art Gallery. However, its antecedents have been traced to at least 1929 when the State College News reported that the Art Department was sponsoring an exhibit of the work of Flemish artists. [1] While a formal gallery or exhibit place did not exist, the Art Department frequently sponsored such events, displaying art work in the hallways of the second and third floors of the Draper building as well often mounting exhibits in room 207 of Draper. In 1957, under the guidance and jurisdiction of Edward Cowley,who joined the art faculty in 1951 and served as head of the Art Department from 1955 to 1975, the Draper Gallery became an official entity. Existing simply as a room on the third floor of the Draper building in which lights and panels were installed, the Gallery nonetheless had an important function in supporting and enhancing the curriculum of the Art Department. Such a space not only allowed students to exhibit their own work but also enhanced the opportunity for them, as well as for members of the community, to be exposed to the work of local and regional artists. [2]
As a part of the new university campus, space in the Fine Arts Building was designated for an art gallery, which was officially opened in the Fall of 1967. The University Art Gallery was intended as a forum for contemporary art in the area. The "the initial exhibitions of the University Art Gallery, notably Nelson Rockefeller's collections and subsequent faculty shows, brought contemporary art of national and international significance to the Albany art public."[3] Furthermore, it has been argued that Rockefeller and the gallery's first director, Donald Mochon "had a vision of a gallery that would become a national show place for contemporary art of a regional, national and international stature."[4]
In 1971 the University Art Gallery, in conjunction with the Schenectady Museum and the Albany Institute of History and Art, enhanced its reputation as a forum for regional artists with the creation of the Mohawk-Hudson Regional Exhibit. Replacing the Artists of the Upper Hudson Exhibit which had been sponsored for over 35 years by the Albany Institute of History and Art, and the Schenectady Regional Exhibit which had been held at the Schenectady Museum for 16 years, the Mohawk-Hudson Regional Exhibit rotated among each sponsoring institution, each setting a different theme for the given exhibit that year.
Following the precedent set in the '20's, the University Art Gallery initially existed as a unit of the Art Department, but from the beginning it enjoyed a considerable amount of administrative and artistic freedom. Edward Cowley stated that he and Donald Mochon agreed that while the Gallery was a unit of the Art Department, its needs were not necessarily synonymous with those of an academic department. They decided that for the Gallery to be an efficient and effective body, it needed a degree of autonomy to operate and make its own policy decisions. Nonetheless, staff members from the Art Gallery played an integral role in the workings of the Art Department, attending faculty meetings and participating in policy decisions. [5]
The partial autonomy of the Art Museum from the Art Department was regularized in the mid- 1970's when the Art Gallery began reporting directly to the Dean of the College of Humanities and Fine Arts. As of 1993, the University Art Museum reports to Dean of the newly created College of Arts and Sciences. The Gallery and subsequently Museum continue to work closely with the Art Department. It plays a role in the M.A. and M.F.A. programs by exhibiting student's final exhibitions. Furthermore, the Art Museum staff often responds to the Art Department's standing invitation for their attendance at Department faculty meetings. Both the Art Museum and the Art Department use such meetings as an opportunity to share, discuss and coordinate their artistic efforts for the University at Albany, SUNY. [6]
In the 1991-1992 academic year the Gallery changed its name to the University Art Museum. [7] In doing so, the Museum has been able to better reflect its role as a space not only for the temporary exhibit of work, but also as a repository for a permanent collection. The educational role of the Art Museum made plain in its mission statement.
"The primary mission of the University Art Museum is public service and education which supports the core curriculum. The museum is a place for the exhibition of art and artifacts that reflect the diversity of peoples, cultures, and life experiences. Through its exhibitions, lectures, sponsored symposia, and film and video showings, the museum affords opportunities for interaction and collaboration among faculty, students and members of the larger community. The museum's program of developing the University's collections of contemporary art serves the artistic community by supporting living artists and preserving their work. It also creates a resource for enriching the campus environment though loans and exhibitions from these collections. Most essentially, the museum itself is a place for informal self-directed learning. The experience is voluntary and may provide a moment of reflection or a chance discovery that moves the visitor in a lasting way." [8]
Donald Mochon was the director of the Gallery from 1967 until his death in 1976. Before joining the staff at the State University of New York at Albany, he served as a professor of architecture at RPI. After his death, Donald Mochon was succeed by Nancy Liddle. Mrs. Liddle, a graduate of Indiana University and a member of the Art Department, had been involved with the Art Gallery from its inception aiding in planning the first year's exhibits. [9] Mrs. Liddle had served as the full time assistant director of the Gallery from 1966 to 1976, and director from 1976 to her retirement in 1993. Currently Marijo Dougherty is serving as the interim director of the museum.
[1] "Art Department Exhibits Flemish Paintings Here", State College News, p. 4, 11-22-29.
[2] Interview with Edward Cowley, Professor Emeritus, 7-19-93.
[3] "Strategy for Documenting 20th Century Art Activity in the Albany Region" developed by the McKinney Library Albany Institute of History and Art, December, 1991, p 26.
[4] Ibid., p. 31.
[5] Interview with Edward Cowley, Professor Emeritus, 7-19-93.
[6] Interview with Marijo Dougherty, Interim Director of Art Museum, 7-27-93. The exact date of the change in reporting relationships remains unclear.
[7] President's Report, 1992, p. 8.
[8] "Mission Statement, University Art Museum," State University of New York at Albany
[9] News Release 77-124, Office of Media Relations, "Nancy Liddle Heads University Art Gallery", 8-12-77, pp. 3-4.
List of Exhibitions
1967 October 5-November 17 Painting and Sculpture from Nelson A Rockefeller Collection
1967 December Jack Bosson: Paintings and Prints
1967 December Jazz Posters (not in archival holdings)
1967 December Recent Works in Fabric, Acrylic, and Stained Glass
1968 January 8-25 A University Collects (NYU Collection)
1968 January 8-25 A Responsive Eye (M.O.M.A)
1968 February 16-March 14 Big Prints (a national invitational)
1968 February 16-March 14 March-April 1
1968 February 16-March 14 William Wilson: Recent Work
1968 February 16-March 14 Munson-Williams-Proctor:Artists of Central New York
1968 May 19-June 9 Monumental Brass Rubbings by Townsend Rich
1968 May 19-June 9 William Clark: Recent Work
1968 May 19-June 9 Faculty Exhibition
1968 May 19-June 9 Student Exhibition
1968 June 30-August 10 Contemporary British Art (M.O.M.A.)
1968 September 15-October 13 The Artist and His Subject (M.O.M.A.)
1968 September 15-October 13 Guggenheim Fellows in Photography
1968 September 15-October 13 Raphael Villamil: Paintings
1968 September 15-October 13 Donald Ogier: Recent Paintings
1968 October 29-November 17 Project Art (not in archival holdings)
1968 October 29-November 17 Carroll Cloar
1968 October 29-November 17 Articulate Subconsciousness
1968 October 29-November 17 Skidmore Faculty Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1968 October 29-November 17 Bette Saberlich: Ceramic Sculpture (not in archival holdings)
1968 December 10 Donald Mochon: Sales
1968 November 28-December 22 Romare Bearden: Recent Work
1968 November 28-December 22 Donald Cole: Paintings
1968 December 3-21 William Wilson: Recent Works
1969 January 7-19 Young Printmakers (not in archival holdings)
1969 January 7-19 Robles and Ehrenhalt: Paintings (not in archival holdings)
1969 January 26-February 16 Alcoa Collection of Contemporary Art (not in archival holdings)
1969 January 26-February 16 Degan Evans: Paintings
1969 March 2-23 Architecture Without Architects
1969 March 2-23 Critics Choice
1969 March 21 Richard and Lee Wilkie in Concert
1969 April 16-May 18 University Wide Convocation of the Arts
1969 May 15 Majority of One: A Celebration of Conscience
1969 May 25-June 8 Faculty-Student Exhibition
1969 June 24-July 14 Six Danish Graphic Artists
1969 July 1-August 17 Twenty Representational Artists
1969 July 1-August 17 Wall Hangings from the Museum of Modern Art
1969 July 1-August 17 Joe Alper - Photographer
1969 September 29-October 19 Kirk Newman: Bronze Sculpture (not in archival holdings)
1969 October 26-November 23 A Leap of Faith: Art from Israel, Margaret Davies
1969 December 15 Green-Backed Money Pincher
1970 January 4-February 22 Contemporary American Painting and Sculpture from the Schwartz Collection (not in archival holdings)
1970 January 4-February 22 William Wilson: Recent Paintings
1970 January 4-February 22 Screen Prints (not in archival holdings)
1970 January 4-25 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Behan, Kerr, Walton, Scully (not in archival holdings)
1970 February Master Thesis Exhibitions: Casper, Frinta, Madden (not in archival holdings)
1970 March 1-22 Posters: International Poetry Forum (not in archival holdings)
1970 March 8 April 5 Passionate Years (Post-Impressionist works on paper from M.O.M.A) (not in archival holdings)
1970 March 8 April 5 Robert Cartmell: Recent Work
1970 April 18-May 10 1970 Student Exhibition
1970 May 7- 10 The Many Sounds of Electronic Music: An International SamplingUniversity Art Museum
1970 May 17-June 7 Faculty-Student Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1970 May 20-June 7 Master Thesis Exhibitions: Nieastri, Skolnik, Starkey
1970 July 1-August 14 Robert Rauschenberg Graphics
1970 August 30-September 27 Constructivist Tendencies (George and Edith Rickey Collection) (not in archival holdings)
1970 October 7-November 3 The Representational Spirit
1970 November 15-December 22 Shozo Nagano: Paintings
1970 November 15-December 22 Marjorie Koster: Prints
1970 December 6-22 Masters Thesis Exhibition: Barsamian (not in archival holdings)
1971 January 18-February 21 Critic's Choice
1971 January 18-February 21 Wayne Lennenbacker: Photographs
1971 February Milton circa Olson, Charles T. O'Reilly: Reception
1971 February 28-March 25 Leonard Rossoman
1971 February 28-March 25 Oswego Exhibition
1971 February 28-March 25 Franz Kafka Exhibition
1971 March 19 HSPCDH
1971 April 1-25 Washington Art
1971 April 1-25 Thom O'Connor: Prints and Drawings University Art Museum
1971 April 1-25 Spring 1971
1971 April 1-25 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Fantauzzi, Fess, Penman and Spaziani
1971 June 23-July Potsdam Prints (from the collection of the State University College at Potsdam)
1971 July 25-August 11 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Chilla, Jogo, Krems, Martin, Rodrigo, Schade, Steinbach
1971 August 29-September 19 Drawing USA/71 (organized by Minnesota Museum of Art)
1971 September 29-October 28 Two Photographers: Alice Wells and Dan Blumberg (not in archival holdings)
1971 September 29-October 28 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Howe and Rheingold (not in archival holdings)
1971 September 29-October 28 Selection `71 - Works from SUNY campuses
1971 October 20-27 Master Thesis Exhibition: Reintsema (not in archival holdings)
1971 November 9-December 12 Ten Artists from the Mohawk-Hudson Region
1971 November 9-December 12 Kenneth Welch: Jewelry
1972 January 16-February 6 Durer and His Time (not in archival holdings)
1972 January 16-February 6 Eight Women Ceramists
1972 January 16-February 6 Xerox Prints by James Tyler Hoare (not in archival holdings)
1972 February 13-March 12 Photographs by Roman Vishniac
1972 February 13-March 12 Prints by Robert Cartmell
1972 February 13-March 12 Illustrations for Children
1972 March 19-April 16 The World Between the Ox and the Swine: Hans Richter
1972 March 19-April 16 New York State Craftsmen
1972 March 19-April 16 Neil Kagan: Photographer (not in archival holdings)
1972 March 19-April 16 Studio Museum in Harlem (group exhibition)
1972 March 19-April 16 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Albert, Blanchfield, Jerome, McSheehy, Salata and Sauter (not in archival holdings)
1972 March 19-April 16 Vietnam: Photo Essay June 18-July 16
1972 March 19-April 16 L'Exposition Exhibition 1972 - co-sponsored by the United States
1972 March 19-April 16 National Commission for UNESCO (not in archival holdings)
1972 July 24-August 4 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Kingston and Kirstel (not in archival holdings)
1972 August 27-September 20 Our Own Things: University Collection (not in archival holdings) Larry Kagan and Sara Skolnik: Recent Works (not in archival holdings)
1972 October 1-November 5 New York Women Artists
1972 October 1-November 5 Photography of Canada (not in archival holdings)
1972 November 15-December 7 Robert Cartmell (not in archival holdings)
1972 November 15-December 7 Africoba (not in archival holdings)
1972 November 15-December 7 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Doody, Moore, Schwabe (not in archival holdings)
1972 December 10-17 Crafts Show: SUNYA Art Students (not in archival holdings)
1973 January 14-March 11 The Civilization of Lluros: Norman Daly
1973 April 2-29 Australian Bark Paintings
1973 April 2-29 Stephen Antonakis: Neons
1973 May 20-June 3 1973 Student Exhibition
1973 May 20-June 3 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Ahern, Goodman, Herschberg, Ross, Thompson and Yohalem
1973 June 24-August 5 Artists of the Mohawk-Hudson Region
1973 August 26-October 2 The Iconography of the Picture Press
1973 August 26-October 2 New Plastics (organized by Dennis Byng)
1973 October 16-November 18 Walter Plate: Paintings, Drawings, Collages
1973 October 16-November 18 Martin Benjamin: photographs (not in archival holdings)
1973 November 26-December 16 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Langbart, Lipka, Price, Tierney and Nielsen
1974 January 13-February 14 Fantastics and Eccentrics
1974 January 13-February 14 Tight and Loose
1974 February 24-March 27 Wayne Lennebacker: Photographs
1974 February 24-March 27 Genocide: Photographs
1974 April 14-May 5 1974 Student Exhibition
1974 May 12-25 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: McDowell, Prince, Roman and Rowland
1974 June 23-July 3 Salon de Refuses (from 1974 Mohawk-Hudson Regional entries) (not in archival holdings)
1974 July 15-August 2 Works on Paper: Thom O'Connor, Robert Cartmell and Peter Jogo
1974 July 15-August 2 Decade: Graphics in the Sixties (not in archival holdings)
1974 July 15-August 2 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Retz, Newby (not in archival holdings)
1974 August 25-October 3 Five Artists from the Mohawk Hudson Region
1974 August 25-October 3 Selection `74: recent acquisitions to the University Collection (not in archival holdings)
1974 August 25-October 3 Monumental Brass Rubbings by Townsend Rich (not in archival holdings)
1974 October 13-November 17 Dan Budnik: Photographs of Albany Medical Center
1974 October 13-November 17 Terminal Iron Works: David Smith at Bolton Landing (not in archival holdings)
1974 October 13-November 17 The Sculpture of Cyprus (Museum of Fine Arts, Boston)
1974 November 24-December 14 Women in France: Photographs
1974 November 24-December 14 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Tarlton and Mendelson (not in archival holdings)University Art Museum
1975 January 19-February 16 Nell Blaine: Paintings
1975 January 19-February 16 William Wilson: Paintings
1975 February 23-March 23 Martha Jackson Collection
1975 February 23-March 23 Tod Bryant: Photographs (not in archival holdings)
1975 March 14 Jazz Live
1975 April 1-28 1975 Student Exhibition
1975 May 4-25 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Ellis, Golash, Ioepitzi, Wawrla, Rivera, Rucker and Zeman-Rogers (not in archival holdings)
1975 June 14- August 7 Exhibition by Artists of Mohawk-Hudson Region
1975 June 30-August 8 55 Mercer Street
1975 July 24-August 8 Art Council Collection
1975 July 24-August 8 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Bernatowitz, Keevil and Stewart (not in archival holdings)
1975 August 25-September 28 Garo Antresian
1975 August 25-September 28 Clinton Adams
1975 October 5-November 6 Gerald DiGuisto Sculpture
1975 October 5-November 6 Irena Altmanova-Frinta: Pastels
1975 November 23-December 21 Coast to Coast Coasters: Organized by Robert Cartmell
1975 November 19-December 5 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Korber, Russ and Walker (not in archival holdings)
1975 December 8-21 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Calo and Edelheit (not in archival holdings)
1975 December 3-21 Mochon Drawings: Auction of 300 drawings by Donald Mochon (benefit for Art Gallery)
1976 January 19-Feburary 15 Paintings by Robert Huot
1976 March 14-April 14 Contemporary American Stage Design (not in archival holdings)
1976 April 9-30 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Jansson, LaPlante, Miller, Moskowitz, Stone
1976 April 9-30 and Turner (not in archival holdings)
1976 April 9-30 Portraits of Edith Rickey
1976 April 9-30 Ceramic Sculpture by Niles Wallace
1976 June 27-August 8 1976 Artists of the Mohawk-Hudson Region
1976 June 28-August 7 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Chamberlain, Chereskin and Armstrong
1976 August 8 Ted Chereskin: An Exhibition of Cast Lucite Sculpture
1976 August 30-September 26 Faculty Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1976 August 30-September 26 Sons and Others: Women Artists See Men
1976 October 3-November 7 The Sculpture of John Ferro
1976 October 3-November 7 The Manipulation of Light: 10 photographers (not in archival holdings)
1976 October 3-November 7 Calligraphic Collages by Wolfgang Roth (not in archival holdings)
1976 November 14-December 19 Paintings by Marilyn Giersbach
1976 November 14-December 19 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Rhodes and Taylor (not in archival holdings)
1977 January 17-February 13 Paintings and Prints by Richard Callner
1977 January 17-February 13 Alvin Napper: Photographs
1977 January 17-February 13 William Cristenberry: Photographs
1977 March 5-31 University-wide Exhibitions by SUNY students
1977 April 11-May 1 Annual Student Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1977 April 11-May 1 Kathleen Grove and Larry List: Recent Work
1977 May 8-29 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Boyer, Garrett, Rivette and Bryant
1977 May 8-29 Medieval Musical Notations: organized by Drew Hartzell of the
1977 May 8-29 University at Albany Music Department (not in archival holdings)
1977 June 26-August 5 Jim Dine Prints
1977 July 16-August 5 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Cho, Davidson and Faiola
1977 July 16-August 5 Annual Faculty Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1977 August 29-September 25 Contemporary Yugoslav Prints
1977 September 30-October 23 Printed Quilts/Quilted Prints
1977 September 30-October 23 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Dougherty and Tsamardinos
1977 October 30-November 27 A Don Mochon Celebration (two copies)
1977 December 4-23 Frances Simches Memorial Exhibition
1977 December 4-23 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Bernatowitz, Buerkley and Johnson
1978 January 23-February 17 Graphic Artists of New York State (not in archival holdings)
1978 January 23-February 17 Fantasy Sculpture: Joan Danziger (not in archival holdings)
1978 February 27-April 2 J. Pindyck Miller: Sculpture
1978 February 27-April 2 Polly Hope: Stuffed Pictures (not in archival holdings)
1978 March 19- April 30 Ed Cowley
1978 April 10-May 1 Annual Student Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1978 May 8-21 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Adam, Bida, Bartholomay, Delis, Golojuch,
1978 May 8-21 Grindle, Gugell, Heikolf, Honon, Kempf, Silver and Lawrence
1978 June 17-September 1 World Print Competition (not in archival holdings)
1978 July 5-August 3 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Blake, Dietrich, Feroleto, Kite and Saddlemire (not in archival holdings)
1978 September 12-October 8 Annual Faculty Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1978 September 12-October 8 On the Offset Press
1978 September 12-October 8 David Hayes: Sculpture Out-of-Doors
1978 September 22-October 22 I Am Not Blind: organized by the Wadsworth Atheneum
1978 October 19-November 20 Tenth Street Days (not in archival holdings)
1978 October 19-November 20 Mohawk-Hudson Invitational: Rheingold and Rymanowski
1978 December 1-21 Young American Printmakers
1978 December 1-21 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Antos, Formanek, Labaree and Mastrianni
1979 January 22-February 18 Faculty Choice
1979 January 22-February 18 S.A.G.A. (not in archival holdings)
1979 March 2-April 1 Mauricio Lasansky
1979 April 17-29 Annual Student Exhibition (not in archival holdings)
1979 May 11-27 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Califano, Colon, Eadie, Graham, Greenfield,
1979 May 11-27 Hogan, Johnson, Leavitt, Malloy, McFerran, Pell, Pletts, Rehm, Spitsbergen and Wager (not in archival holdings)
1979 June 25-July 29 1979 Artists of the Mohawk-Hudson Region
1979 August 28-September 23 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Hall, Rounds, Witkowski and Woolsey (not in archival holdings)
1979 August 28-September 23 Traditions in American Basketry
1979 October 6-November 18 The Sculpture of Richard Stankiewicz 1953-1979
1979 December 4-20 Irish Tinkers: Photographs by SUNYA Anthropology
1979 December 4-20 Professor George Gmelch
1979 December 4-20 Eight from the Northern Interior: Handmade Books and Broadsides
1979 December 4-20 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Brownell, Dutt, Edgar, King, Meyers, Holdridge
1980 January 22-February 29 The American Landscape: Paintings by Allan D'Arca
1980 January 22-February 29 Phyllis Galembo: Recent Color Photographs (not in archival holdings)
1980 January 22-February 29 Archaeology--Past, Present, Future: Photographs (not in archival holdings)
1980 March 14-April 20 Dorothea Lange: Her Collection (not in archival holdings)
1980 March 14-April 20 Jason Stewart: Works on Paper (not in archival holdings)
1980 May 6-25 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Giscombe, Harland, Kim, Levitt, Mulero, Rosenthal, Tansey, Strauss, Townsend
1980 July 8- August 31 Clay, Fiber, Metal (not in archival holdings)
1980 June 24-August 1 Mowhawk-Hudson Regional Art Exhibition
1980 September 4-October 5 The Sculpture of Hugh Townley
1980 September 4-October 5 Invisible Light: Infrared Photographs (organized by Robert Cartmell)
1980 October 18-November 23 U.S. Eye: Photography (organized for 1980 Olympics) (not in archival holdings)
1980 December 2-18 Masters Thesis Exhibitions: Gessinger, Kingsbury, Langworthy, Robert